# **Neil Ashton**

neil.m.ashton@gmail.com (804) 731-5209

## **ROLES**

#### PROGRAMMER

Extensive experience in data visualization (JavaScript + D3.js) and functional programming (Clojure, Haskell). Worked on high-impact, tight-deadline projects for Global Witness. Deep knowledge of computational linguistics and natural language processing (Python + NLTK, Grammatical Framework, XFST).

## RESEARCHER

Accomplished in both academic and non-profit settings. Experienced in formal sciences (computational linguistics), humanities (philology), and policy (open data).

#### WRITER AND EDITOR

Writing and editing professional with a decade of experience. Experience working with publication tools including Lagarantees, and Jekyll. Editor of volume of major linguistics publication.

## **EXPERIENCE**

• TECHNICAL WRITER, ANALYST, AND DEVELOPER, Open Knowledge (2013 – Present)

Developed high-impact interactive data visualizations for clients. Researched problems in open data policy and data specification development. Wrote documentation for software projects. Processed data using Python and Clojure. Worked remotely with international team and minimal supervision.

• GRADUATE RESEARCHER, Cornell University (2009 – 2013)

Applied computer science to problems of natural language. Taught workshops on specialized programming techniques (Markov Logic Networks, Grammatical Framework). Presented research at conferences and published in proceedings.

• EDITOR, Proceedings of Semantics and Linguistic Theory (2011 – 2012)

Proofread and edited all submissions for 21st volume of conference proceedings. Worked with authors to ensure adherence to style guidelines. Published online using eLanguage CMS.

## **EDUCATION AND AWARDS**

• MASTER OF ARTS (ABD), Linguistics, Cornell University (2009 – 2013)

Received four-year SSHRC Doctoral Fellowship (in lieu of offered Joseph-Armand Bombardier CGS Doctoral Scholarship).

• MASTER OF ARTS, Classics, University of Alberta (2007 – 2009)

Recipient of eight honors and awards.

• BACHELOR OF ARTS, Classics, University of Alberta (2002 – 2007)

Recipient of eleven honors and awards.